# 這個魚缸那麼大 魚又那麼少
This fish tank is so big, but there are so few fish.
# 我去搞點
Let me get,
# 再搞點回來
get some more fish.
# 太少啦 不好看
Too few, it doesn't look nice.
# 這種地方很多那個蛇頭魚的哦
There are a lot of snakehead fish in this kind of ponds, you know.
# 把那草割一下
Let me cut away the grass,
# 我們好放個地籠下去
so that I can drop a trap here.
# 這麼多草 地籠都放不下去
It's not possible to put the trap with so much grass.
# 這個小地籠
This is a small trap.
# 這裡放個小地籠
I'm gonna put a small trap here.
# 加點料下去
Let me put some bait.
# 這個料是我祖傳秘方哦
The formula of the bait is my ancestral secret.
# 等它可以進去下裡面吃得去 (註︰是我中文不好嗎？沒聽懂沒看懂)
The fish can get in, go down inside and eat and whatever.
# 你看 剛好沉下去啦 這樣
Look! It sinks to the bottom, you see.
# 準備一個大地籠
Let me get a big trap ready.
# 這草要搞乾淨
The grass needs to be cleared away.
# 不然放不下去
There are no rooms for the trap otherwise.
# 誒 怎麼還是小的
Eh? Why is it still a small one?
# 有大的 裡面還有大的 還有兩個大的
There are big ones, there are big ones inside, two big ones.
# 沒 就4個 我剛放掉了
No, I have only four. I've already put them down.
# 再帶了兩個過來
I've brought two more here.
# 你在哪裡放掉了
Where did you put them down?
# 車裡
Inside the car
# 就用這個小的
So I'll just use this small one.
# 有貨的話
My love depends of the result,
# 小的也是愛
not the size.
# 已經放好兩個啦 就這麼小的潭有兩個夠啦
I've already put two. Two would be enough for such a small pond.
# 我們還放下面
Let's put more down there,
# 放下面放兩個下去
down there, two more down there.
# 你看 就那個水潭
Look! That pond,
# 去那裡
we'er going there.
# 肯定有魚
There must be fish.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 這個地籠放好啦
So the trap is placed.
# 我們明天再過來看
Let's come again tomorrow.
# 肯定有魚的這裡
There will certainly be fish.
# 這個垃圾處理一下
We need to take care of the garbage.
# 好啦 先回去
Alright! Let's go back first.
# 第二天
The next day
# 今天過來收一下地籠哦 就在那下面 看一下有沒有魚
We're coming to get back the traps today. They're right down there. Let's see if there are any fish.
# 按道理來說 應該有魚
There should be fish, theoretically.
# 不然沒道理呀
It doesn't make sense otherwise.
# 吃都沒吃
The bait is still there, untouched.
# 你看 都沒有哦
Look! There's nothing.
# 那麼奇怪
It's strange!
# 放回去
Put it back.
# 我就不信
There must be fish.
# 沒有魚
I know it.
# 好息
It stinks!
# 誒 有 有兩條
Eh? Here, here are two!
# 一條 有一條蛇頭魚
One, one of them is a snakehead fish.
# 有
Yup!
# 你看 這有
Look! Here are...
# 哇 好多小魚
Wa! A lot of small fish.
# 你看
Look!
# 一條蛇頭魚喲
Here's a snakehead fish.
# 把它放桶裡面
Let me put it into the bucket.
# 誒 這裡還有
Eh? Here are still more.
# 哎呀 可以喲
Aya! Not bad!
# 還有一條那大的泥鰍
Here's also a really big loach.
# 哇 夠大吧 這泥鰍
Wa! It's a huge loach, isn't it?
# 把它這個網放回去
Let me put the net back.
# 我把它放回去啦
I've put it back already.
# 我們看一下明天有沒有貨
Let's see if we can have anything tomorrow.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 上 上面還有兩個籠
There, there are two more traps up there.
# 去看一下
Let's have a look.
# 還有兩個地籠那邊放著
There are two more traps on that side.
# 現在下去
Let's go down there now.
# 要從這個懸崖峭壁上
We need to walk slowly,
# 慢慢的走下去
along this sheer cliff.
# 你看 那個魚在動
Look! That fish, it's moving!
# 哇
Wa!
# 大收獲哇
It's a fruitful day!
# 哈哈 兩條哦
Haha! Two fish,
# 又看到兩條魚在這裡
I see two fish here!
# 哈哈哈
Hahaha!
# 想跑
Wanna run away?
# 沒那麼容易
Nothing can be more difficult.
# 你看
Look!
# 夠大吧 這兩條
These two are huge, aren't they?
# 你看 這條就夠大吧 這條
Look! This one is enormous, isn't it?
# 這有一條
Here's one more.
# 不要這些S的 (註︰是不是國內都忌諱「死」字？)
I don't want the dead ones.
# 這還活著的
And these are still alive.
# 不要
Not this one
# 你看 我把它這籠子再放回去
Look! I'm gonna put this trap back again.
# 還有的 不止那麼一點點
There are more fish, more than the tiny little bit here.
# 我去看一下別外一個地籠
Let me take a look at the other trap.
# 滿收獲哦
Fruitful, fruitful!
# 3條
Three fish!
# 看有沒有第4條啊
Let's see if fourth fish is there.
# 哎 額 一條蛇
Ay! Ey! There's a snake!
# 好大條哇
It's very big.
# 你看 那一條蛇哦 怎麼搞
Look! There's a snake. What should I do?
# 小魚就有
Only small fish
# 有蛇哦 也有蛇頭魚
There are snake, and snakehead fish.
# 把那蛇放出來
Let me get the snake out.
# 太厲害啦
Amazing!
# 一冕就搞到那麼多蛇頭魚
I can have some many snakehead fish in just one night!
# 出來 出來 出來
Get out, get out, get out!
# 蛇 你快點出來
Come out, snake!
# 快點走哦
Go 'way!
# 出去喲
C'mon, get out!
# 不然的話
Otherwise,
# 等下帶回你去
I'll take you home.
# 哇 這條蛇頭魚
Wa! This snakehead fish...
# 這條蛇頭魚 稍微小一點
This snakehead fish, it's a bit smaller.
# 這 這種地方很多那個蛇頭魚的
There, there are a lot of snakehead fish in this kind of ponds.
# 放回去
Put it back.
# 這樣放著
Leave it here.
# 明天又有貨
Tomorrow is another fruitful day.
# 洗一下手
Wash my hands.
# 今天 你看
Today, look!
# 那麼多魚
We have so many fish.
# 你看 把它倒出來
Look! Let me pour them out.
# 哇
Wa!
# 又搞了那麼多條
We have so many fish again.
# 這個泥鰍才大 看到沒
This loach is enormous. Can you see it?
# 我都沒見過那麼大的泥鰍
It's the biggest loach that I've ever seen.
# 這蛇頭魚
This snakehead fish
# 哇 這兩條可以 這個是
Wa! These two fish are not bad. This is,
# 應該是母的這條 那麼大的肚子
this should be female. It has such a big belly.
# 把它放到那個魚缸裡面去養
Let's put them into that tank and keep them there.
# 那麼[SIC]蛇頭魚不能放下去
I'm not gonna put the snakehead fish here.
# 放下去的話等下會跑啦
They would run away otherwise.
# 把這些小的放下去
I'm gonna put these small ones here.
# 你們自由啦
You're free now.
# 嘴巴好像 嘴巴這裡都有點受傷啦
The mouth seems, the mouth is a bit wounded here.
# 這樣沒辦法
Well, anyway
# 它撞籠子撞的
Cuz it crushed onto the trap.
# 你看 它這身上
Look! Its body,
# 好靚哦
is really beautiful!
# 它這個應該是 母的
I think it should be, female.
# 養起來 讓它下崽
Let's keep it, and let it give birth to babies.
# 剛好看到我老媽在這裡打田 我也過來幫忙打一下 (註︰「老媽」這個說法較粗俗，要對應一下)
I just come across my ma and she's ploughing. Let me help her.
# 然後 然後再把那個秧子 扔下去
Then, then we'll take the rice seedlings, and shoot them onto the field.
# 直接扔下去就可以了 拋秧苗
We can shoot them right away. It's called seedlings shooting.
# 這個 要把它
These seedlings, need to be,
# 一棵一棵
shot onto the field,
# 往那邊丟
one by one.
# 搞準一點
I need to aim well.
# 以前要插秧的 現在不用插啦
We needed to plant the seedlings in the past. But it's no more necessary.
# 現在直接這樣
Now we can simply,
# 丟就成啦
shoot them right away.
# 扔不準
I aim bad.
# 我扔不準 很難扔哦
I can't aim well. It's really hard.
# 一扔就歪啦
It never goes straight.
# 這個要有點技術的哦 不是
It needs some techniques, you know. You want to do it,
# 不是想扔就扔得準的
doesn't mean you can do it.
# 我扔的都有點歪歪的
And I'm not doing it very well.
# 這水有點深
The water here is a bit deep.
# 這樣不要緊的
Never mind.
# 丟 丟順手了就很 很好丟了
It becomes much, much easier once you know the tricks.
# 丟了也比較直一點了
And the seedlings are standing upright,
# 不會東倒西歪了
instead of swinging here and there.
# 扔的越遠 丟的越準
The further I shoot, the better I aim.
# 哇 真是的
Wa! It really works.
# 這樣一天應該也扔不了多久
I don't think I can spend a long time doing it a day,
# 扔不了多少畝吧
I mean I can't cover a large area in a day,
# 應該一畝地
only about one "mu" (666.7 square metres)
# 最快都是一畝地
at most one "mu".
# 這乾農活
This job,
# 這樣的速度 好累呀
together with this speed, it's really tiring.
# 應該買 買一個插秧機回來
I should have, I should have bought a planting machine.
# 但是我們這邊的田全是丘陵
But our fields here are all along the hills.
# 不是丘陵 就是
Not exactly hills, it's like,
# 每 每一塊地都是很小的
each, each piece of land is a tiny one.
# 插 插秧機使不上勁
The, the planing machines can't help much.
# 全靠人工的 種 種下去
So they're plant, planted, all by hands.
# 所以這個
So, it's a,
# 很辛苦的哦 種田
it's a really tough job, I mean farming.
# 但是 也要種一點啊
But, we need to do it, though we don't do much.
# 這些稻子都是 每年都是我們
The rice here is, every year, we
# 自家耕的田
we plant on our own fields.
# 種一點稻子
We plant some rice,
# 到時候就不用買了
then there's no need to buy.
# 自己想要多少米
Whenever we want rice,
# 直接用
we can ah,
# 直接去
I mean we can simply,
# 碾出來就行了
mill however much we want right away.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 沒這個秧子了
I've run out of seedlings now.
# 我去看一下那個地籠
Let me take a look at the traps,
# 看下地籠有沒有魚
and see if there are any fish in the traps.
# 準備回去了
Let's get ready to go back.
# 哇 又一條蛇哦
Wa! Snake again!
# 哎呀 一條泥鰍
Aya! A loach,
# 小魚
and small fish
# 全是小魚跟一條蛇
All are small fish, and a snake,
# 還有一條小蚄蟹 誒呀
and a small crab too, eya!
# 把蛇放出來
Let me get the snake out.
# 這個蛇是沒毒的
This snake is not venomous.
# 快點 出來 出來 出來
C'mon! Get out, get out, get out!
# 你自由啦
You're free now.
# 往下面走哇
Go downwards!
# 不走等下
Just go! Otherwise...
# 放到桶裡面來
Let me put it into the bucket.
# 這個蛇笨的要死
It's a goddamn stupid snake.
# 那麼笨 下去耶
Get down! Stupid!
# 快點下去
C'mon, hurry up!
# 為甚麼不下去
Why isn't it going down?
# 不下去我把你帶回家的哦
If you are not going, I'll take you home, you know?
# 快點出去
Get out! Now!
# 它蛇頭在這裡
It's head is here.
# 你自由啦 還不快點出
You're free now. Why don't you just go?
# 不出的話 等下我帶回去家裡去哦
Go before I change my mind! Otherwise I'll take you home.
# 又搞了一些魚
So I still have some more fish,
# 只是不多而已
just not too many.
# 我們再放 明天
Put it here again. Tomorrow,
# 再過來看一下 看有沒有
let's come again and see if there are any.
# 去上面看一下
Let's have a look up there.
# 那邊還有兩個地籠
There are two more traps.
# 看一下還沒有
Let me see.
# 全是小魚 那麼小不要啦
All are small fish. I don't want them. They're too small.
# 明天再過來看
Let's come again tomorrow.
# 再放一晚上
Leave it here for another night.
# 有就有
This is the last time,
# 沒有就沒有
no matter we have anything tomorrow or not.
# 額 沒有
Eh, nothing.
# 肯定白天它不出來
They must be hiding themselves in daylight.
# 我今天早上看了一下
I came here and took a look this morning,
# 抓了幾條回去
and have caught some fish back home.
# 要晚上
At night,
# 要過一冕上看一下
leave it here one more night and have a look.
# 如果明天沒有就
If we still can't get anything tomorrow,
# 把這網起啦
we're gonna get back the net,
# 換另外一個地方
and place it at another place.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 回去啦
Let's go back!
# 空軍 一條都沒有
Empty-handed! Not even one fish.